Gamma Kappa Phi; Records ua800.005
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Gamma Kappa Phi Sorority Records
1920-2012
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua800.005
1.87 cubic ft.
The Gamma Kappa Phi Sorority Records contain documents related to the history, activities and alumnae of the Gamma Kappa Phi Sorority at the University at Albany.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Several individuals have donated materials for this collection including John Schneider, Class of 1965 (2010) and Susan Gardner Boyle, Class of 1963 (2014).
Biographical Sketch
In 1913, 15 female students at what was then the New York State Normal College (now the University at Albany) formed a club they called Theta Rho. The students, who roomed together at 186 Western Avenue in Albany, drafted a constitution and held regular meetings. New members were brought into the club each year.
In the 1917-1918 school year, the organization re-wrote its constitution and renamed itself Gamma Kappa Phi. Members rented their own house at 36 Nineteenth Street (currently Winthrop Avenue) and held a formal initiation for the first time. In 1919, Gamma Kappa Phi petitioned to become an official sorority of the New York State College for Teachers (the school's name in that time period). The petition was granted in April 1920, and Gamma Kappa Phi was admitted to the Intersorority Council.
Over the ensuing decades, the sorority lived at a number of locations in downtown Albany until, in the 1960s, its members along with the other Greek organizations at the University were moved into the dormitories on the Uptown Campus. Gamma Kappa Phi is no longer an active sorority at the University at Albany. The organization closed in the 1970s, like many other local sororities, because of dwindling membership.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of bound volumes of administrative records, photographs, scrapbooks, clippings, memorabilia, and Gamma Kappa Phi alumnae activity materials.
Of interest is the recording secretary's book, which has a history of Gamma Kappa Phi from its formation until 1951, and meeting minutes from 1920-1939. There is another record book with meeting minutes and attendance lists, dating from 1963-1967. Two alumnae books include lists of Gamma Kappa Phi alumnae and records of payment of alumnae dues. There are files with treasurer reports, meeting minutes, information about sorority housing, alumnae directories and newsletters of alumnae life post-graduation.
In addition, there is a photograph album which belonged to house mother Grace Nye and includes images of sorority members on campus (and later of their families which they sent to Nye) from 1946-1961. The scrapbooks date to 1970-1971 and have photographs of the sorority's activities from those years.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged chronologically. There are no series.
Greek letter societies--New York (State)--Albany; Women--New York (State)--Albany--Societies and clubs; Scrapbooks; UAlbany Student Groups; Minutes (administrative records); State University of New York at Albany; Gamma Kappa Phi Sorority
- Recording Secretary's Book, 1920-1939 (Oversize 1)
- Alumnae Book, 1920-1946 (Oversize 1)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1928-1931; 1987-1988; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Ninth Annual Reunion, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Alumnae Association Newsletters, 1930-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "And the Lamp Went Out", 1937; 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- House Mother Grace Nye's Photograph Album, 1946-1961 (Oversize 3)
- Alumnae Association Reunion Meeting Minutes, 1946-1972; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Photographs, 1947-1954; 1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Treasury Record Book, 1948-1955 (Oversize 1)
- Banners, ca. 1951; Undated (Oversize 3, Folder 1)
- Alumnae Directories, ca. 1954; ca. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Alumnae Book, 1956-1957 (Oversize 1)
- Gamma Kappa Phi, Inc. Certificate of Incorporation, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Composite Photographs, 1959-1963 (Oversize 3, Folder 2)
- Alumnae Association Newsletters, 1960-1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Gamma Kappa Phi, Inc. Financials and Treasurer's Reports, 1963; 1966-1969; 1971-1973; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Constitution and By-Laws, 1963-1964; 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Housing Including Sales of 410 Hudson Avenue and Move to Uptown Campus, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes correspondences from Dean of Students about planned accommodations for Greek organizations on new Uptown Campus and procedures sororities and fraternities must follow.
- Record Book, 1963-1967 (Oversize 1)
- Director and Annual Meeting Minutes and Notes, 1963-1972; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1964-2000; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Alumnae Association Treasurer's Reports and Invoices, 1968-1973; 1982; 1993-1994; 1996-1999; 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Scrapbook, 1970 (Oversize 2)
- Scrapbook, 1971 (Oversize 2)
- House Mothers' Plaque, 1984 (Oversize 2)
- Alumnae Association Newsletters/Directories, 1984; 1987; 1990; 1995; 2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Coffee Hours and Feedback Forms, 2001-2002; 2010-2012 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Gamma Kappa Phi Bucket Hat, Undated (Oversize 3)
- Gamma Kappa Phi Jacket, Undated (Oversize 3)
  Green with yellow lettering.
- Gamma Kappa Phi Sweater, Undated (Oversize 3)
  White with green lettering.
- Gamma Kappa Phi T-shirt, Undated (Oversize 3)
  White with yellow and green lettering.
- Sorority Songs, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)